On December 12 2025 a report was
released.  It was written by the former
CEO of ASML, the most important [music]
company in Europe.
The CEO was asked to research the Dutch
economy and find out how future [music]
is looking.  And his answer was, "It's
not looking too hard."  You say [music]
our prosperity is at stake.  And so
we are not just talking about
companies, but actually about all of us
[music] and what we all
earn together.  How urgent is that?
I think it is very [music] urgent.
A nation is dragging into stagnation.  A
welfare state [music] no longer pay for
geopolitical threats power against bills
and taxes are high.
Netherlands will have increased taxes or cut
important services.
This is the story of a terrible thing
happening in the Netherlands.  It's a
story of one of the most important
reports [music] in recent Dutch
history.  And it's a report why the
Netherlands is slowly dying.
foral
[music]
sitation
economic Europe has
[music] decades that is
[music]
Mario s shock waves through EU trade
China is very much
less
competing with us in global markets on
all accounts [music] for years Europe's
economy has been growing more slowly but
that was mostly fine there only [music]
a few smalls
weve
enerch
[music] compan over
willers
[music]
disappearing
market
more than we have to lean on
productivity
productivity is weak very productivity
gap grew but this was mostly fine Europe
[music] is different  strength isn't
growth at all costs
Americans bigones guns cars [music]
more disposable income Europeans have
security a lower salary but not [music]
fired as easily an imperfect but
actually functioning healthc system
[music] we have strong education we
have healthc system that works as I said
we have good welfare [music] system and
then we have lots of specific radiant
urbanism where they can drink bewer
[music]
some high taxes
money is [music] everything until it is
countries go broke grad and then all at
once to aging population European
[music] spending on  pensions and health
is to  explode with rush doorep
moreend [music] on
them
[music]
Gre chose austerity and lost the
generation to Turkey chose inflation and
wiped out middle class savings.
Argentina defaulted and it still hasn't
recovered.  If you have growth, future
taxes can keep pace with future
spending.  But Dutch and European growth
is declining
like trying to squeeze a juiced out
orange slowly but surely there isn't
enough economic activity to tax.
Europe's biggest obstacle isn't lack
[music] of talent, will or ability
fragmentation Europe's internal barriers
are essentially 44% [music] ter already
scale you need to create international
competitors just isn't there.  The US
doesn't need to be a good market, it's
simply a bigger one.  If Europe wants to
stay competitive, we need to support
European innovators which is why I'm
excited to be sponsored by Udo.  It's an
own one management software offering
entrepreneurs a complete suite of
applications designed to simplify the
day-to-day management of their business.
It's based in Belgium with a European
founder.  We have more than 45 easy to
use applications covering sales,
accounting, project management, website
creation, human resources and more.  Udo
provides everything a business needs in
one place.  It brings all your
applications into one unified platform.
It's fully integrated app share data in
real time linking sales, accounting and
inventory for smoother operations.  With
one subscription, I can get access to
all the apps that UD has to offer
[music] starting from 19.90 a month.
And even better, the first application
is totally for free with unlimited
support and hosting included.  I don't
want to be a fearmer, but if like me in
a European country and the recent
developments in the US make you
uncomfortable, next time you're paying
for a new software, maybe consider
looking around on UD to see if they have
a more affordable solution that does
exactly the same thing.  Link in the
description.
So in the aftermath of Drag's report,
the Dutch Minister of Economic Affairs
asked Peter Venik to come up with a
similar report specifically focusing on
the Netherlands.
For years ran ASML, a Dutch company that
manufactures the world's best chipming
machines.
The way we
organized it is we organized well over 30
tables, round round tables.
At every table, there was actually a reflection
of the organizations
working on the economic
development of this country.  The
conclusion was bleak.  If it stays on the
same course, the country will go broke.
That means that within 5 years we
will have to start cutting back on
practically everything.  On education, on
safety, on healthcare, um on uh the
infrastructure.
The uh Dutch house every Dutch
household will have €7,000
net less to spend in 10 years nets
connected to global markets unlike
Germany depend on energy intensive heavy
industry and doesn't have China knocking
it doesn't share France's luxury boomer
benefits approach to budgeting that
takes from the young with ASML it has an
international technological
niche more leverage than most EU
countries but the Netherlands does have
a few problems
But what has become clear to me in
those 30 ground tables
is that those ideas do exist.
I will go into that in a bit more detail later, but it is
not going to happen.
Car created the world but the Dutch made
the Netherlands.  Unlike France, Germany
or the US, it's always been shaped by
one unique [music] constraint.  It
doesn't have enough land.  Half the
country is farmland.  Around 12% of space
in Netherlands [music] is covered by
manmade surfaces nearly three times the
European average.  It's one of the most
[music] densely populated countries in
the world.
Americans room to sprands
every square meter is zero game.
Dutch [music]
colors are very closely
related, but they said it is this
color sky blue, while the permit
in the permit states light blue.
[music] It is this color.  When mills
abstract people's views, house building
makes too much noise.
Because of density, the Dutch power grid
is also filled to the brink.
[music]
If you need a large connection,
you can wait 8 to 12 years.  It has to
do with regulations, among other things, and
costs us between 10, perhaps even 30
billion per year.
Dutch electricity prices
are so high that they are driving the
energy-intensive [music] industry
out of the country.
Netherlands intoibility
add of space on the ground [music]
suffers of space air.  Near everything
useful can do with land causes nitrogen
pollution.  Agriculture, home building
and transportation infrastructure create
gases like ammonia that harm the
environmental human health.
In most of Europe the gas is
distributed, but in the Netherlands it is a literal Dutch
oven. There are too many cow factories and cars to build up, and the area is suffering because
nitrogen levels vastly exceed
European limits. It builds nothing; all
permitting procedures in the Netherlands take
months at best, but
often years.  And that, for example,
hinders the expansion of the infrastructure.  Els,
in other countries things go much, much
faster.  And then I look at the
nitrogen lock.
The nitrogen lock,
um, will cost us about 30
billion in revenue by 2030.  Um, I think that 23% of
all investment proposals
to carry out the energy transition are simply
stalling, so because of regulations.
We cannot go any further.
ve tradeofs may less housing that more
controversial
the lack of space exasperates problems
that are faced by everyone in Europe for
decades like other European countries
the Dutch economy grew simply by putting
more people to work baby boomers and
women entered the labor market people
came in from abroad were plenty of hands
building and growing the economy was
easy while the number of workers
increased each worker productivity went
up.  Mass education meant they worked
more efficiently creating more value per
worker
because both the numbers of workers and
the value created per worker increased
the economy boomed but this is now
changing in the past 20 years two-thirds
of economic growth have come from a
larger labor force and not from growing
productivity the classic way to increase
productivity is through education
despite the Netherlands being a
well-educated country Dutch performance
has been dipping for years.  But if we
look at performance in
education, it has been declining for 20 [music] years.
We are below the
USO average.
And uh [music], if you look at the
so-called PISA scores—which are scores
for basic skills in language and
mathematics and in uh uh [music]
so physics—then that is not a downward
trend.  That is a trend that looks like a
collapsed, uh, graph.
EU toppers education Dutch
teagersovakia.
In mathematics alone,
40% less music material is
offered than 30 years ago.  And the
other countries actually invested in
excellence.  In Dutch tertiary education
number of students that choose technical
degrees is among the lowest in Europe.
20 years of decline despite successive
governments money into education.
Luckily, if education decline, Dutch
resourcefulness can be observed.
But despite the Netherlands having a
reputation for Calvin shame, [music]
there isn't a single country in the
world with a higher of part workers.
Dutch people work 1450 [music] hours
per year on average compared to 1740 on
average in the OECD
that chill out lifestyle is
understandably celebrated trying too
hard would be cringe a Dutch person can
live comfortably without having to live
a rat race life there's no need to be
[music] extra it's all true but it does
also mean that Dutch women earn less
over their lifetimes than the Netherlands almost
anywhere else in Europe
despite the progressive
reputation [music]
lower annual
Dutch women
factors taxes are
what you [music] actually  want to be.  If
I look at where we
get our tax revenue from and
compare that with our neighboring
countries, we collect relatively little
tax from wealth tax on
private individuals.  Hm.
Then we collect a relatively large amount of tax,
but well, the money has to be
raised from income tax anyway.  So
you could say that we are becoming, or rather are becoming,
a kind of rentier economy more than other countries,
while we are actually making
the hard-working Dutch
pay for it with higher taxes and
higher income tax rates.
Dutch nurse works.
If all part-time nurses were to work an
extra day, that would create the
equivalent of 11,000 extra full-time
nurses.  This would almost solve the
entire shortage and the average nurse
still wouldn't be working full time.
Leave it to Dutch culture and financial
incentives to make that switch
impossible.
And even if Dutch people were to start
working full time overnight, that still
wouldn't solve its low growth.  Because
of aging there inevitable heart ceiling
on how much working longer hours can
bring about.  [music]
Much of Dutch prosperity comes from an
open economy that trades with other
countries.  It has the largest port in
Europe and its economy fundamentally
depends on free trade.  Unfortunately,
the world's largest and second largest
economies both use trade as a weapon.  A
tiny country that depends on two big
guys playing by the rules will be eaten
for dinner.  Poor independent.
Luckily in his report Venic at least
offers some ideas to break the
stagnation whether they all individually
desirable is a separate matters
to build [music] a 22.5 billion AI giga
factory.  He wants to sell state owned
enterprises so the Netherlands can make
drones, launch its own satellite fleet,
power its ships with nuclear reactors.
There's been much debate about Venic
specific prescriptions, but nobody
really disagrees with his diagnosis.
The Netherlands needs to modern its
labor market, change education system,
make hard choices about how to use
limited space more efficiently
clear [music]
things are
comfortable.
This summer, Dutch politicians spent
days talking about a mean tweet by
countryer Bob.
I think most Dutch people are sitting at home watching [music] thinking, "Yeah, why is
n't it about housing construction or the
economy?"
kill wolf his name was Br he make it
this is not quite the mindset report
calls for and the choice is clear you
can't have a world welfare state with a
part economy and a mindset
linked ven report below also made a new
channel to talk about how the
Netherlands is changing that dives into
more nich dutch topics
new videos are coming soon you should
probably subscribe don't that's also He.
[music]